Guide to the Earle Sumner Draper, Sr. papers, 1933-1969
Draper, Earle Sumner Sr. papers, 1933-1969
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Earle Sumner Draper, Sr. papers, 1933-1969
2745
Earle Sumner Draper, Sr., 1893-
1.3 cubic ft.
Articles, speeches, correspondence, books.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Primarily articles and speeches of Earle Sumner Draper, Sr., city planner. Also includes correspondence concerning a conference on urbanism held in Cambridge, Massachusetts in March 1942.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Earle Sumner Draper, Sr. received a B.S. in landscape architecture from Massachusetts State College in 1915. He then joined the staff of John Nolen, city planner, of Cambridge, Massachusetts, and was appointed Nolen's southern representative. For two years he was engaged in town planning, including the layout of Kingsport, Tennessee. In 1917 he established his own firm in Charlotte, North Carolina, becoming the first professionally trained city planner in the Southeast. Draper was involved in the planning of industrial towns, as well as parks, universities, schools, cemeteries, private estates, golf courses, land subdivisions, and landscape projects. In 1933, he left private practice to take the post of Planning Director for the Tennessee Valley Authority. He later advanced to Director of Regional Planning Studies at the TVA; and initiated the planning and construction of the town of Norris, rural freeways, powerhouses, and dams. In 1940 he left the TVA to become assistant administrator of the Federal Housing Administration; he was later appointed deputy commissioner. After World War II, he returned to private practice.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Primarily articles and speeches of Earle Sumner Draper, Sr., city planner. Also includes correspondence concerning a conference on urbanism held in Cambridge, Massachusetts in March 1942.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Draper, Earle Sumner, Sr., 1893-; United States. Federal Housing Administration.; Tennessee Valley Authority.
Subjects:
City planning.; City planners.
Places:
Kingsport (Tennessee)--City planning.; Norris (Tennessee)--City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Speeches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Speeches
  - "Regional Planning in the Tennessee Valley Area," Baltimore Maryland, October 11, 1933 (Box 1)
    9 pp. typescript
  - "The Town Planning Movement," Knoxville, Tennessee, September 26, 1933 (Box 1)
    5 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft
  - Notes on speech to the Tennessee Garden Clubs, Knoxville, Tennessee, May 2, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech "Land Planning and Housing Activities," Knoxville, Tennessee, May 4, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech, "Country Life Ideals of TVA," Amherst, Massachusetts, May 11, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech, "Regional Planning," Cambridge, Massachusetts, May 11, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech to State Teacher's College, Johnson, Tennessee, June 29, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech to the City Planning Institute, St. Louis, Missouri, October 21, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Large Scale Regional Development," St. Louis, Missouri, October 22, 1934 (Box 1)
    11 pp. typescript. Summary of above speech, 3 pp. typescript
  - Notes on speech, "Land Planning Activities of the TVA and the Significance of Education," Knoxville, Tennessee, October 26, 1934 (Box 1)
    2 pp. typescript, with additional notes
  - "Regional Planning and the Tennessee Valley Authority," Cambridge, Massachusetts, January 14, 1935 (Box 1)
    16 pp. typescript
  - "Shall We Plan for the Future? Long Time Planning and Coordination of Planning Functions," Boston, Massachusetts, January 21-22, 1935 (Box 1)
    Landscape Architecture, July 1935, 4 pp. with notes
  - "Land Planning in the Tennessee Valley," Washington, D.C., March 1, 1935 (Box 1)
    Radio talk, 3 pp. typescript
  - "Regional Planning for the Development of Land and Water Resources," Eugene, Oregon, March 26, 1935 (Box 1)
    29pp. typescript with notes. Text of speech in The Commonwealth Review, March-May 1935, 19pp.
  - Notes on speech, "Regional Planning," Eugene, Oregon, March 27, 1935 (Box 1)
  - "Housing is More than Building Construction," Atlanta, Georgia, May 3, 1935 (Box 1)
    Bulletin of Georgia School of Technology Proceedings of the Conference of Low Cost Housing, 11 pp., July 1935 issue, notes
  - "The Development of a United Land Program," Knoxville, Tennessee, June 22, 1935 (Box 1)
    13 pp. typescript, with notes, 3 additional drafts. Edited version in University of Tennessee Summer Sessions Report, 6 pp.
  - "Applied Home Economics in TVA Houses," Chicago, Illinois, June 25, 1935 (Box 1)
    Journal of Home Economics, 8 pp. December 1935, read by Marie White
  - "What Price Land Waste," Knoxville, Tennessee, July 15, 1935 (Box 1)
    5 pp. typescript, notes
  - Notes for a talk before Fairfield County Planning Association, Bridgeport, Connecticut, July 24, 1935 (Box 1)
  - "The City's Part in Regional Development," Knoxville, Tennessee, October 22, 1935 (Box 1)
    Public Management 4 pp. November 1935
  - Notes on "Regional Planning," and summary of the talkSavannah, Georgia, December 5, 1935 (Box 1)
    3 pp. typescript
  - "Development of an Idea in Connection with Discussion of Land Planning," Knoxville, Tennessee, 1936 (Box 1)
    13 pp. typescript, 2 additional drafts plus notes
  - Notes on "Regional Planning," Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes on speech in Dayton, Tennessee, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "What the Construction of Chickamuga Dam Will Mean to Chattanooga," Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes on talk in Tupelo, Mississippi, April 23, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Notes on talk to TVA employees on Chattanooga, Chattanooga, Tennessee, April 24, 1936 (Box 1)
  - "Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow," Chattanooga, Tennessee, May 28, 1936 (Box 1)
    8 pp. typescript with notes
  - Notes on "Regional Planning in the Tennessee Valley," Memphis, Tennessee, April 13, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Notes, Knoxville, Tennessee, May. 7, 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Where City and Country Meet," 9 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft, plus notes, Detroit, Michigan, June 1, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Notes of speech to new TVA employees, Knoxville, Tennessee, September 23, 1937 (Box 1)
  - "The Testimony of a Planner," Knoxville, Tennessee, March 4, 1938 (Box 1)
    5 pp. typescript, notes included
  - Notes of Speech to the Engineer Club, Knoxville, Tennessee, March 14, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "The Improvement Campaign of 1902-1906 ,Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, May 6, 1938 (Box 1)
    " 17 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft plus notes
  - "Parkways and Freeways," Norris, Tennessee, May 13, 1938 (Box 1)
    7 pp. typescript plus notes
  - "New Developments in the Planning Field Bearing on the Problems of Municipal Planning," Minneapolis, Minnesota, June 21, 1938 (Box 1)
    4 pp. typescript, notes
  - Speech at inauguration of Radio Station WNRA, Muscle Shoals, Alabama, Nov 17, 1938 (Box 1)
    8 pp. typescript, notes
  - Notes on "Our Southern Heritage in Gardening," Norris, Tennessee, Jan 10, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Changing Elements on the Growth of Knoxville," Knoxville, Tennessee, March 3, 1939 (Box 1)
  - "Planning for Water Recreation on a National Scale," Santa Fe, New Mexico, October 8-10, 1939 (Box 1)
    5 pp. typescript
  - Notes on speech at a conference on Planning Problems and Administration, Chicago, Illinois, January 19, 1940 (Box 1)
  - "The Next Stop in Highway Planning," University of Tennessee, March 14, 1940 (Box 1)
    19 pp. typescript, notes
  - "New Recreation Opportunities in the Tennessee Valley," Knoxville, Tennessee, April 22, 1940 (Box 1)
    18 pp. typescript, notes,
  - "The Tennessee Valley Authority and Social Welfare," notes, Jacksonville, Florida, April 24, 1940 (Box 1)
    20 pp. typescript
  - "Urban Development in the Southeast: What of the Future?," Chapel Hill, North Carolina, May 3, 1940 (Box 1)
    13 pp. typescript, notes
  - "Private Enterprises in Defense Housing," The Review of the Society of Resident Appraisers, November 1940, Chicago, Illinois, November 12, 1940 (Box 1)
    15 pp. typescript; notes, 2 additional drafts, 6 pp. article
  - "The FHA and Decentralization," Springfield, Massachusetts, November 20, 1940 (Box 1)
    2 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft, notes
  - "Urban Redevelopment - High Lights and Side Lights," Extract in Public Management, May 1941, Cincinnati, Ohio, April 17, 1941 (Box 1)
    18 pp. typescript, notes, 1 additional draft
  - "'Time is of the Essence' - In Planning," Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, May 12, 1941 (Box 1)
    1 additional draft, notes, 9 pp. typescript
  - "FHA in the National Defense Effort," Washington D.C., May 16, 1941 (Box 1)
    11 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft, notes
  - Notes for Speech of Testimonial Dinner for W.J. Lockwood, Newark, New Jersey, May 23, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes for Speech at University of Southern California Institute of Government, June 9, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Discussion Leader at National Housing Inventory, Washington, D.C., June 11, 1941 (Box 1)
    Notes
  - Notes on "Demands of Modern Life in Cities," and additional notes, Falls Village, Connecticut, August 6, 1941 (Box 1)
  - "Rebuilding Programs and the Government," Baltimore, Maryland, October 23, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Putting Plans into Action," Ann Arbor, Michigan, November 4, 1941 (Box 1)
  - "How Can Our Cities Rebuild," New York City, November 7, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Can We Rebuild Our Cities," Advanced Press Release on " Urban Redevelopment," Cleveland, Ohio, November 18, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Problems of War Housing," additional notes, New York City, March 26, 1942 (Box 1)
  - "War Problems of Private Housing," New England Federal Savings League, Bulletin, Boston, Massachusetts, September 19, 1942 (Box 1)
    7 pp.
  - "War Housing in 1943 ," Chicago, Illinois, February 6, 1943 (Box 1)
    2 pp. typescript with additional 1 draft
  - Notes on talk at FHA 608 Meeting, New York City, February 18, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Notes on "Problems of Housing in the Postwar Period," Richmond, Virginia, February 23, 1943 (Box 1)
  - "Postwar Financing of Private Housing," Omaha, Nebraska, June 14-16, 1943 (Box 1)
    8 pp. typescript, read by Flavel Shurtleff
  - Notes on speech to the Seattle Chamber of Commerce, Seattle, Washington, July 20, 1943 (Box 1)
  - "Objectives and Techniques of Postwar Planning," Buffalo, New York, September 27, 1943 (Box 1)
    17 pp. plus 3 previous drafts, typescript - notes, Press Release, 3 pp. typescript
  - Speech before Northeast Federal Savings League, Boston, Massachusetts, November 6, 1943 (Box 1)
    13 pp. typescript, 2 drafts
  - "Speech of November 6 given before New Orleans Builders, Lenders, Etc.," (Radio Speech), November 27, 1943 (Box 1)
    13 pp. typescript; Press Release, 3 pp. typescript
  - Notes on speech to Louisville Real Estate Board, additional notes, Louisville, Kentucky, April 28, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "Urban History is City Planning History," Washington, D.C., May 30, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes of speech made on West Coast trip, July 9-25, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Untitled, October 1946 (Box 1)
    2 pp. typescript
  - "Plan and Performance," Chicago, Illinois, November 19, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Speech at PHMI Annual Meeting, Chicago, Illinois, March 30, 1948 (Box 1)
    1 pp. typescript
- Additional speeches
  - Press Release - 59th Annual Meeting of American Forestry Association, 1936 (Box 1)
    3 p. typescript, 1 additional draft, App.
  - Untitled, 1936 (Box 1)
    3 pp. typescript, App.
  - Untitled, June 19, 1941 (Box 1)
    7 pp. typescript
  - Correspondence, Urbanism Conference, Cambridge, Massachusetts, March 5, 1942 (Box 1)
  - "Home Building Industry in Wartime," St. Louis, Missouri, November 18, 1942 (Box 1)
    6 pp. typescript, 1 additional draft, notes
  - "National Association of Home Builders," Cleveland, Ohio, November 16, 1943 (Box 1)
- Articles
  - "Activity in Southern Mill Village Development," Textile World Journal, February 7, 1920 (Box 1)
    1 pp. reprint
  - "Southern Mill Village Development," Textile World, February 3, 1923 (Box 1)
  - "Mill Village Developments," Textile World, February 9, 1924 (Box 1)
  - "Southern Textile Village Planning," reprint from Landscape Architecture, October 1927 (Box 1)
  - "Proposed City Planning Improvements for an Industrial Section of La Grange, Georgia," The American City, June 1930 (Box 1)
    2 pp. reprint
  - "The New T.V.A. Town of Norris, Tennessee", November 24, 1933 (Box 1)
    Press Release, 4 pp. typescript
  - "Housing the Workers at Norris Dam", November 25, 1933 (Box 1)
    Press Release, 5 pp. typescript, notes
  - "The T.V.A. Builds a New Town," for Junior League Magazine, December 1933 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Freeway Will Be a Landscaped Highway of Natural Beauty," The Knoxville News-Sentinel, January 21, 1934 (Box 1)
    2 pp.
  - "Mild Climate of Tennessee Valley Allows Use of Porches at Norris," The Knoxville News-Sentinel, February 25, 1934 (Box 1)
    1 pp.
  - "Homes at Norris Will Have Simple Beauty," The Knoxville News-Sentinel, February 25, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "The Regional Approach to the Housing Problem," prepared for Duke University Law School Quarterly, April 1934, March 18, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Tennessee Valley Authority Notes", June 16, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "The T.V.A. Town of Norris, Tennessee," for American Civic Association Annual, August 1934 (Box 1)
    4 pp. typescript
  - "Land Planning Activities of the Tennessee Valley Authority", August 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Coordinated Planning in the Tennessee Valley", September 11, 1934 (Box 1)
    4 pp. Press Release, notes
  - "T.V.A. Develops a Wilderness Park", October 3, 1934 (Box 1)
    5 pp. typescript Press Release
  - "T.V.A. to Build Fish-Nurseries", October 4, 1934 (Box 1)
    2 pp. typescript Press Release
  - Press Release, October 16, 1934 (Box 1)
    1 pp. typescript, notes
  - "The Work of the Land Planning and Housing Division," for Information Division, Fall 1934 (Box 1)
    3 pp. typescript, notes
  - "The New T.V.A. School at Norris, Tennessee," American School and University Annual, Fall 1934 (Box 1)
    4 pp.
  - "The T.V.A. Freeway," for American Civic Association Annual, Fall 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Forestry and Regional Planning," American Forests, April 1935, October 18, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "The Community of Norris," for Information Division, November 1934 (Box 1)
  - "The New Town," My Garden and Home, December 1934 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Low Cost Housing," for National Association of Housing Officials Annual, December 1934 (Box 1)
  - Statement: Prepared for Atlanta, Georgia, Conference on Low Cost Housing, May 3-4, 1935 (Box 1)
  - "Housing by the T.V.A.," for American Planning and Civic Annual, August 12, 1935 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Planning in Practice," for American Planning and Civic Annual, August 15, 1935 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A.'s Yardstick for Housing," The Architectural Forum, September 1935 (Box 1)
    8 pp., 1 additional draft
  - "Land Planning in the Tennessee Valley," Plan Age, December 1935 (Box 1)
    6 pp.
  - "The Shopping Center and Town Offices at the T.V.A. Town of Norris, Tennessee," for the Architectural Record, July 1936 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Activities in Landscape Architecture," for Landscape Architecture Magazine, August 1936 (Box 1)
  - "Freeway Design Principles Applied on a Rural Road," Engineering News-Record,; "The T.V.A. Freeway Proves Itself", November 12, 1936 (Box 1)
  - "The Freeway Principle of Highway Design", March 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Demonstration Parks in the Tennessee Valley", March 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Levels of Planning," The Planner's Journal, March-April 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Demonstration Parks in the Tennessee Valley," for Architectural Record, April 1937 (Box 1)
    12 pp. typescript
  - "Demonstration Parks in the Tennessee Valley," Parks and Recreation, April 1937 (Box 1)
    15 pp.
  - "Demonstration Parks in the Tennessee Valley," Parks and Recreation, April-May 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Demonstration Parks in the Tennessee Valley," Parks and Recreation, May 1937 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Repairs Oust Termites," reprint from American Builder and Building Age, August 1937 (Box 1)
    3 pp.
  - Report on Baltimore - Washington - Annapolis Area (E.S.D. consultant), Regional Planning, November 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Much Ado About Something - Housing," reprint from The American City, December 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Tennessee Valley Low-Cost Housing," for American Architecture, February 1938 (Box 1)
  - "T.V.A. Low Cost Housing," rejected by American City, February 1938 (Box 1)
    11 pp. typescript
  - "T.V.A. Housing Development at Pickwick Dam", March 1938 (Box 1)
    19 pp. typescript
  - "What Is This Planning Business," The Chattanooga News, July 26, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Press Release - Speech at Banquet Inaugurating Radio Station WNRA, Sheffield, Ala. 8 pp. typescript, November 18, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "Regional Planning in Practice as Illustrated by T.V.A.," Extrait Des Comptes Rendus Du Congres International De Geographie, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "Regional Planning," chapter in Planning for America by George Galloway, (H. Holt and Co. Publishers, New York), January 21, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Article for Architectural Forum, Postwar Pattern Series, notes, August 1941 (Box 2)
  - Above article condense for Insured Mortgage Portfolio, "The Problem of Urban Redevelopment", September 1941 (Box 2)
    7 pp., notes
  - "Administration of Priorities," United States Investor, May 16, 1942 (Box 2)
  - "Planning for Adjustment to Changing Conditions," The American City, May 1944 (Box 2)
    2 pp. with notes
  - Notes on FHA Financing, January 2, 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Old Houses in Urban Communities," for Better Homes and Gardens, Harper's Magazine, Architectural Forum, August 9, 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Housing," a paragraph, House and Garden, February 1947 (Box 2)
- Books
  - Greer, Guy, ed. The Problem of the Cities and Towns. Conference on urbanism. Harvard University, (Earl Draper was a participant.), March 5-6, 1942 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Federal Housing Administration. A Handbook on Urban Redevelopment for Cities in the United States. Washington, 1941. (E.S. Draper, Assistant Administrator) (Box 2)